Hi everybody.
大家好
We are the Harvard Callbacks
我们是"哈佛召回"组合
We have a special Valentine's Day message
想向教员和同学们
dedicated from the teaching staff to the students.
传达一份特殊的情人节讯息
I will never find another lover sweeter than you,
再也找不到比你更甜蜜的爱人
sweeter than you
比你更甜蜜
I will never find another lover more precious than you,
再也找不到比你更珍贵的爱人
more precious than you Coz you are Close to me you're like my mother,
比你更珍贵 因为你我 亲如母女
Close to me you're like my father,
你我 亲如父子
Close to me you're like my sister,
你我 亲如姐妹
Close to me you're like my brother
你我 亲如兄弟
You are the only one my everything
你是唯一 我的一切
and for you this song I sing All my life
我会永远为你唱这首歌
I pray for someone like you I thank God that I,
我祈祷有人如你  感谢上帝
that I finally found you
我终于找到你
And I pray that you do love me too Pray
我祈祷 你也爱我 祈祷
that you do love me too
你也爱我
Happy Valentine's Day!
情人节快乐
Hi, morning.
早上好
You know, when I asked them to dedicate this song,
请他们献歌时
I had a slightly different song in mind.
本来想选另一首歌
But-- so be it.
但是…算了吧
We do love you.
我们确实爱你们
What we are going to talk about today,
今天课程的内容
continuing from last time
是上节课的延续
is or are the basic premises of this course--
是这门课的基本前提
where we are coming from, where we are going--
"我们来自哪里 我们将去哪里"
laying down in many ways,
从各个方面展开论述
the foundation of the spiral that
螺旋的基础
we are going to create for the next semester together.
我们将在本学期一起创建它
Last time we stopped, we talked about how difficult change is.
上次我们讲到改变有多么困难
We talked about the Twin studies that illustrate
我们谈到"双胞胎研究" 举例说明了
that what Lykken and Tellegen said--
Lykken和Tellegen提出的
maybe changing our happiness level is as difficult as--
也许改变我们幸福水平
and futile-- as trying to change our height.
和试图改变身高一样困难和徒劳无功
And we talked about the error of the average and the mistake
然后谈到这些研究学者么犯的
that these researchers are making,
一般性的失误和错误
misunderstanding the nature of change.
误解改变的本质
Because if someone changes,
因为如果一个人在改变
the question is no longer "is it possible to change"
问题已不再是"是否可能改变？"
but rather "how is it possible to change".
而是"怎样才可能改变"
And then we talked about the Somerville Cambridge study
还谈到剑桥-萨默维尔研究
that show that literally the Rolls-Royce of interventions failed--
证明劳斯莱斯干预彻底失败
5 years with the leading scientists,
五年来 剑桥 哈佛和麻省理工的
researchers, psychiatrists,
顶尖科学家 研究人员
psychologists from Cambridge, Harvard and MIT,
精神病专家和心理学家
putting their minds and hearts for good intentions
沥尽心血 带着美好的意图
to bring about change-- failure.
实施改变 但最终失败
Not only they have failed in bringing about positive change,
不仅没有实现正面的改变
they actually brought about negative change.
实际上是带去了负面的改变
Remember?-- Alcoholism rates went up for the intervention group,
还记得吗? 干预组的酗酒比例
compared to the control group.
和对照组相比是增加的
The control group that joined no intervention actually
未参与干预的对照组
were more luckily to advance in their workplace 20, 30 years later.
更有可能在二三十年后获得升职
So change is difficult,
改变是困难的
but then we went over and said,
但我们又说
"Well, Marva Collins creates change.
"Marva Collins实现了改变
So it is possible.
所以改变是可能的"
Programs by Martin Seligmen and Karen Reivich
Martin Seligmen和Karen Reivich
and numerous others succeeding in bringing about change".
及大量学者都成功地实现改变
And the challenge then is,
困难在于
for us, if our goal is to become practical idealists
如果我们想成为实践理想主义者
is to understand what it is that brings about change and then do it.
就要理解是什么带来改变然后去做
Spread the word.
传播理念
Spread the word about the research.
传播研究的理念
Even if the research doesn't always communicate good news,
即使研究并非总是传达好消息
it's about communicating what works,
它传达的是行之有效的方法
what is real, as opposed to our dreams ,
可为的方式而不是空洞的梦想
our desires, our hopes, our wishes--
渴望 希望 愿望
that's not enough.
那远远不够
Good will, idealism, good intentions are not enough.
好的意愿 理想主义 好的意图是不够的
We need to be grounded in research.
我们需要扎根于研究
And this is very much what Maslow has in mind
这正是Maslow的想法
when he talked about the analogous Manhattan Project,
当他谈及类似的曼哈顿计划时
where scientists, positive psychologists or that time psychologists,
科学家 积极心理学家 当时的心理学家
social scientists would get together
社学科学工作者聚在一起
and pick out the tip of the stem--
在流行学术领域中挑选出
the few ideas,
几种观念
the few programs that work and then replicate them.
几个有效的项目 再复制它们
Study the best and as one of the students here, Mariam --
研究最好的 正如Mariam同学
came to me after the class and she said,
课后找到我时说的
"the tip of the stem is actually about democratizing excellence."
"流行学术其实是要将杰出大众化"
I love that phrase.
我喜欢这个说法
Democratizing excellence--
将杰出大众化
studying the best and applying it to the rest of us.
研究最好的再应用在其他人身上
Ok, so we have this grand scheme,
我们有了这样一个伟大的计划
grand idea by Maslow to create a Manhattan-type Project.
有了Maslow创造类似曼哈顿计划的伟大想法
But what if I'm not interested in going into one of these projects?
但是如果我不想参与计划？
What if I'm not even interested in becoming an academic?
不想成为学者
Just want to do things on my own: Can I make a difference?
只想做自己的事 我能否实现改变？
And the answer is absolutely yes.
答案是 绝对能够
One of the most significant barriers
人若想在世间有所为
to people doing things in the world,
真正实现改变
to actually introducing change
面对的最显著障碍之一
is that they underestimate their ability to bring about change.
是他们低估自己实现改变的能力
There is a lot of research in psychology.
心理学界有很多研究
Primarily the people who started are Emerson and Moscovici
爱默生和莫斯科维奇是先驱
and many others who have done research showing how minority--
他们和其他学者都证明少数人
very often one person can make a big difference,
经常是一个人 如何实现重大改变
can make a significant difference.
能实现显著的改变
Ralph Waldo Emerson:
爱默生说
"All history is a record of the power of minorities,
"人类历史是少数派
and of minorities of one,
和一个人的少数派的权力记录
"-- a lot to backed that up in social science research.
很多社会科学研究支持这个观点
Margaret Mead, the anthropologist:
人类学家Margaret Mead说
"Never doubt that a small group of thoughtful,
"永远不要怀疑一小群
committed citizens can change the world.
有思想 坚定的市民可以改变世界
Indeed, it is the only thing that ever has."
事实上 正是这群人改变着世界"
All change begins in the mind of single person or a small group."
所有改变从一个人或一小众人的思想开始
And then it expands.
然后不断扩大
Now the question is "how does it expand"
问题是"它如何扩大"
and "why is it so difficult for us to understand,
以及为什么我们难以理解
accept, assimilate and live according to the fact
我们能够做出改变这个事实
that we can make a difference,
并接受 被同化以及据此生活
if we understand that what we need to understand
如果我们能了解我们需要理解的
is how change happens.
是改变如何发生
Change happens exponentially.
改变以指数级发生
Our connection to other people and their connection to others
我们与其他人的联系及他们与更多人的联系
and so and so create an exponential function
形成了一个指数函数
which explains for an example--
可以用你们熟习的
that those of you are familiar with-- "butterfly effect"
"蝴蝶效应"为例加以解释
how a butterfly flapping its wings
一只蝴蝶在新加坡拍动翅膀
in Singapore can theoretically cause a tornado in Florida.
理论上能在佛罗里达引起龙卷风
Because on particle hits another and another and another.
原因在于粒子的连续碰撞
It also explains the phenomenal 6 degrees of separation:
它也解释了六度分隔理论
how we are all connected and interconnected
我们都是关联和相互关联的
in a web potentially of goodness.
在一个潜在善的网络里
To illustrate the exponential nature of human networks,
为了说明人类网络的指数本质
let's look at smiles.
我们来以笑为例
What do we know from research is that smiles are contagious.
研究证明笑有传染性
Someone smiles-- makes you smile.
别人笑会引起你发笑
You smile-- you make someone smile.
你发笑会引起别人发笑
And so on and so on.
以此类推
You know, even some goes pass you on the street and you don't smile
即使路人与你擦身而过时 你没笑
ostensibly you don't smile--
表面上你没有笑
there are certain micro-muscles in your face
但你面部的细微肌肉
that are moving that actually make you feel better.
会收缩 让你感觉更好
So smiles are contagious.
笑是传染的
Now if you smiled to--
如果你的笑
or make three people smile,
感染了三个人
and these three people--
这三个人
each one makes three other people smile.
每个人又引起另外三人发笑
And those nine people make three--
那九个人
each one-- three other people smile.
每个人再用笑容感染三个人
Within 20 degrees of separation from you
只需要20度的分隔
initial smile to the three people,
从你用笑容感染三个人开始
the entire world will be smiling.
全世界就会笑起来
Exponential nature of social networks.
社会网络的指数本质
The same with making other people feel good--
让别人感觉良好也有感染力
complimenting people.
恭维别人
If you make three people--
如果你能让三个人
or even better, four people a day feel good and they make--
甚至四个人度过美妙的一天
they pay it forward and make four others feel good,
他们会推展 让四人有美好的一天
and so on and so on.
以此类推
Within very little time,
只需要很短的时间
the whole world will be made to feel better.
整个世界都会感觉更加美好
This is the nature of an exponential function.
这是指数函数的本质
So smiles and laughters are contagious.
笑和笑声是传染的
And to illustrate, I want to show you a quick video.
为了说明这一点 我会插播一段录像
(Spanish) (The sentence shown on the screen at the end,
（西班牙语）
"Dificil, eh?" means " Difficult, isn't it?")
很难不笑 不是吗?
Alright. I have to see this one more time.
我要再看一遍
Sorry.
报歉
So the theme of the class today is babies.
今天讲座的主题是婴儿
We are going to see another one soon.
一会还有另外一段
So let's understand: what is the nature of exponential function
让我们先理解指数函数的本质
so that we can understand the power of one?
以便理解"一"的力量
I'm looking for someone to make a deal with me.
我想找个人和我作个交易
Here is the deal: What I am going to do is ask you--
交易是这样的 我要做的是要求你们
this is all voluntary,
纯属自愿
you don't have to do it-- here's the deal.
可以不做 交易是这样的
I am going to ask you to give me each day--
我要求你们每天给我…
or rather I'm going to give you,
还是我给你们吧
whoever signs the deal with me,
我给每个和我作交易的人
1000 dollars every single day for the next 30 days.
每天一千美元 连给30天
And what you will give me in return is on the first day,
你们给我的是 第一天
one cent-- one penny;
一分钱
on the second day, two cents; third day, 4 cents...
第二天 二分钱 第三天 四分钱
Every day, twice as much as the previous day,
每天给我前一天的两倍钱
starting with one.
从一分钱开始
Who would like to make this deal with me?
谁愿意和我作这笔交易？
Again, every day I give you for the next 30 days 1000 dollars.
我会在未来30天每天给你一千美元
What you'll do is every day for the next 30 days give me one cent,
你们要做的是在未来30天给我一分钱
next day two, four, eight and so on.
第二天二分 然后是四分 八分 以此类推
Anyone? Any takers?
任何人?谁想做这笔交易?
One.
一个人
Looking for some more.
还有吗？
So that's 30000 down for me.
我少了三万美元
Anymore? Ok, good.
还有吗? 很好
Alright. So here' s the deal.
好 是这样
Here is what will happen.
结果将是这样
On the 30th day, I will give you another 1000 dollars--
在第30天 我再给你一千美元
you'll have a total of 30000 dollars from me.
你将从我这里一共得到三万美元
On the 30th day, I will be getting from you in total,
在第30天 我将从你那里一共得到
including the first 29 days--
包括前29天
no, rather on the 30th day,
不 在第30天
I'll be getting from you 5,368,709 dollars and 12 cents.
我将从你那里得到5368709.12美元
Double that, times by two,
再翻倍 乘以二
this is the money I will be making in one month.
这将是我在一个月赚到的钱
One cent on the first, two on the second, and so on.
第一天一分钱 第二天二分钱…
For most people, it seems extraordinary
很多人会觉得不可思议
because people don' understand the nature of exponential function
因为他们不懂指数函数的本质
and therefore don't understand the nature of the power of one.
也不懂"一"的力量
Here is another example.
再举一个例子
Just kidding. I'll let you off the hook.
开玩笑的 我放过你
Another example. This captured my imagination--
另一个例子 这个例子捕获了我的想象力
when I was a kid,
在我小的时候
my dad told me about the invention of the chess game--
父亲给我讲象棋游戏的由来
some of you know the story.
有些人可能知道这个故事
So the inventor of the chess game--
象棋游戏的发明人
he was in India, and went to the local king.
他在印度 去见当地的国王
The king was very impressed with the game and said,
国王很喜欢这个游戏并说
"How can I reward you?" And the chess player said,
"我要如何奖赏你?" 象棋发明者说
"No, it' OK really."
"不必 真得不用奖赏"
The king said, "No. I want to reward you.
国王说"不 我想奖赏你
How can I rewards you?"
我要怎样奖赏你?"
So the inventor of the chess game said,
于是象棋发明者说
"Ok. What I like is on the first block,
"好吧 我希望
first square,
在第一个方格上
I would like one grain of rice.
我想要一粒大米
On the second, I'd like two grains of rice.
在第二个方格上 我想要两粒大米
On the third, four grains of rice and so on and so on.
第三个方格四粒大米 以此类推
That's my request."
那就是我的要求"
And the king said, "Are you sure that's all you want?
国王问"你确定只想要那么多?
I'm prepared to give you a lot.
我可以给你更多奖赏
This is a wonderful game."
这是一个很好玩的游戏"
And the inventor said, "Yes."
发明人说"我确定"
So the king told his assistant to go and get the man,
国王指示助手
give the man his wish.
去实现他的愿望
When they started to calculate
当他们开始计算
how much rice would be need to fill up all blocks,
需要多少粒米填满所有方格时
all the way to 2 to the power 63.
从第二格到第63格
They realized that the rice could
他们发现米粒
fill up the entire world with a thick layer.
能厚厚地覆盖全世界
Again, misleading--
再一次 误导…
fail to understand it because we don't understand
没有理解指数函数 因为我们不理解
the nature of exponential change.
指数变化的本质
Another-- last one.
最后一个例子
So how many time do you think--
你们认为需要折多少次
you all have a piece of paper in front you--
你们面前都有一张纸
how many time do you think you need to roll over the piece of paper
你们认为需要将纸折叠多少次
for the piece of paper to reach the moon?
才能碰到月亮?
The moon, 240000 miles awaya from us.
月亮离我们24万英里
How many times do you need to fold the piece of paper
需要折纸多少次
so that you can reach the moon.
才能碰到月亮
41 times.
41次
So if you can have a piece of paper here,
如果你们有一张纸
and you fold it 41 times by the end of the class,
再在下课之前折叠41次
you can reach the moon.
你就能碰到月亮
I don't know why they make such a big deal out of
我不理解人类登月
the person landing on the moon.
有什么大不了的
Seems quite simple to me.
在我看来很简单
And here is the point.
得出的结论是
We underestimate our capacity to affect change.
我们低估影响改变的能力
Because we underestimate the growth of exponential function.
因为我们低估了指数函数的增长
We are influencing people and the world every minute of our lives.
我们活着的每分钟都在影响世界和他人
The question though is in which direction are we going to do it.
问题是我们选择哪个方向
Are we going to be a force for change? Be deliberate?
是成为推动改变的力量?深思熟虑？
Be practical idealists?
成为实践理想主义者?
Or just have the good intentions without the effort
还是只有好的意图但不付出
that's necessary to bring about a positive exponential function.
必要的努力发挥正面指数函数的作用
The final project for this course,
这门课的最后一份作业
as you know is a presentation that you'll give
是由你们做一次报告
whether it's for the (?) students or the extension school students.
选修和专修学生都要做
You'll be giving a lecture to other people.
你们要准备一次讲座
And when we put together the class,
我们在组织课堂时
this is precisely what we thought about:
心中就有这个想法
how you affect change and those people whom you change
你如何影响改变 那些被你改变的人
will hopefully influence others and so on and so on.
希望能进一步影响其他人等等
In many ways, the idea was taken from the film "Pay it Forward".
从许多方面 此想法取自电影"让爱传出去"
What I want to do now is show you a quick excerpt--
我想插播一段片段
just the coming soon of "Pay it Forward",
引出接下来的话题"让爱传出去"
for those of you who haven't seen it.
为那些没看过电影的同学
Because in "Pay it Forward",
电影"让爱传出去"
they capture this very idea of
深刻地描述了
human networks as exponential functions.
人类网络是指数函数的观点
We underestinmate our capacity to effect change
我们低估了自己影响改变的能力
because we underestimate the growth of an exponential function
因为我们低估了指数函数的增长
What if the world is just a big disappointment?
如果世界只是个巨大的失望会怎样?
Unless you take the things that you don't like about this world
除非你把在这世上讨厌的事物
and you flip them upside down and you can start that today.
翻转过来 你们可以从今天开始
That's me.
这是我
And that's three people.
这是另外三个人
And I'm going to help them.
我准备帮助他们
And they do it for three other people.
他们每人再帮助三个人
And they do it for three more.
再每人帮助三个人
It has to be something really big.
但必须是很重大的帮助
Something they can do by themselves.
他们无法自己做到的事
is it possible let one idea to change the world
一个想法可能改变世界
Lost your car?
车坏了?
That's a keen observation.
很敏锐的观察力
I can help you.
我能帮你
You are giving me a brand new Jaguar and you don't want anything.
你给我一辆崭新的捷豹但不要回报
Call it generosity between two strangers.
你可以称为陌生人之间的慷慨解囊
What did you tell my son
你对我儿子说了什么
to make him bring homeless man into my house?
让他把一个流浪汉带回家?
I've got a story, Ok?
我有新闻 相信我?
A senior partner of Chandling and Moss is giving away new cars?
Chandling and Moss的高级合伙人往外送新车?
Just pay it forward.
把爱传出去
Three big favors for three other people.
帮三个人三个大忙
You can't just put two people together and make them like each other.
不可能把两个人放在一起令其彼此喜欢
It's the one.
就是它
Pay it forward. Pay it forward.
把爱传出去
Just like the idea.
喜欢这个主意
You could fix a person.
你可以改变一个人
Do you want to come in and stay?
想进来留下吗?
- It's just complicated.     - Come in.
这很复杂 进来
Supposed to be something hard.
本来就该很困难
I don't care about your burns,
我不在乎你的烧伤
Eugene, if that's even what they are.
Eugene 如果那是你的顾虑
Is that what they are?
那是你顾虑吗?
I can't.
我不能
So sorry.
我很难过
Don't tell me how sorry you are for me.
别说你有多为我难过
Maybe you are scared to get rejected;
也许你害怕被拒绝
well, I can't reject you, you're too quick for me!
我无法拒绝你 你变得太快
Are you still going to pay it forward?
你还会向外传递爱吗?
Give her another chance for me.
为了我 再给她一次机会
You will miss!
要来不急了
I wanna wear the green dress.
我想穿那条绿色的裙子
No, you smell good!
不 你很香
- Are you sure?      - Yeah, yeah!
真的? 是的
Pay it forward is a movement in LA, Mrs. McKenney.
"把爱传出去"是洛杉矶兴起的一场运动
- Come on!       - A movement?
别说笑 一场运动?
So you are like flunk us if we don't change the world?
要是我们不改变世界 你会让我们不及格
You might just scrape by with a C.
你可能只得一个C
Impact three people.
影响三个人
Each impact three others and three others.
每个再影响三个 以此类推
Within 20 degrees of separation.
经过20度分隔
You can change the world, the entire world.
就能改变世界 整个世界
Premise number 3: .
第三个前提
internal factors versus external factors.
内在因素和外在因素
There is a lot of research showing
很多研究表明
how difficult it is to change happiness based on external factors.
基于外在因素改变快乐很难
Research on subjective wellbeing--
对幸福的研究
the term that psychologists use to capture happiness essentially
心理学家用这个词来描述快乐
has been going on for very, very long time.
已经进行了很多年
Until recently, most of the research was conducted,
直至最近 多数完成的研究
was done using questionnaires.
使用的都是问卷方式
And many people rightfully so questioned the veracity,
很多人置疑问卷的
the value of these questionnaires,
真实性和价值
because it is subjective--
因为它是主观的
are we measuring something real?
我们是在测量真实的东西吗?
Over the last few years,
过去几年
what started to happen is more and more psychologists
呈现的情况是越来越多心理学家
have been using brain scans for example;
使用大脑扫描
they've been using fMRIs, EEGs, other physiological measures.
使用功能性磁共振成像 脑电图及其他手段
And what they found interestingly is that
他们的有趣发现是
there is a very high correlation
两者有很大的关联性
between the "objective" measures such as brain scans,
在所谓的客观手段 如大脑扫描
such as EEGs, such as fMRI, such as physiological measures
脑电图 功能性磁共振成像等生理学手段
and people's evaluation of their wellbeing--
和人们对自己的幸福的评估
in other words, subjective levels of happiness.
换言之即快乐的主观水平
Very high correlation between the two which in many ways
两者有很大关联 这在很多方面
gives credence to the many years of research that has been conducted,
给多年来进行过的研究提供了可信度
before we have the technology to do it in a more sophisticated way.
在拥有技术进行更全面的研究之前
So the research I am going to share with you--
我会和大家分析讨论各种研究
some of it is taken using the brain scans,
有些使用大脑扫描
other is self-evaluation.
其他是自我评估
But again, both are meaningful as well as valuable.
两者同样有意义有价值
We'll get more into the way that the research is conducted
我们会深入讨论研究的进行方式
when we talk about phenomenon such as meditation.
当我们谈到冥想等现象
Or people like Richie Davidson actually scanned the brain
或像是Richie Davidson 通过扫描大脑
and showed significant changes
显示八周的冥想项目
as a result of an 8-week meditation program.
可以产生重要改变
Or people like a very young Joshua Greene,
或年轻的Joshua Greene
who does a research on morality
他对道德进行研究
and shows that we have morality centers in our brain.
显示大脑里有道德中心
So it's becoming much more sophisticated,
手段更成熟
much more interesting and the interesting thing
更有趣 有趣的是
about it is that it verifies a lot of the research
它验证了许多至今通过不全面的方法
that has been done to date with far less sophisticated means,
所完成的研究的正确性
such as self-repport.
像自我评估
Research done by Daniel Gilbert
Daniel Gilbert所作的研究
who teaches Psych1 on effective forecasting.
他教初级心理学的"有效预测"
Here is one of his studies.
以下是他的一个研究
So what he did was go to professors
他所做的是去访问
who were just before either getting the tenure decision:
接受终身职位审核前的教授
so either they were going to get the tenure or not.
他们要么得到要么得不到
And he asked them, "How happy are you going to be,
他问他们"你会多快乐
if you get the tenure?"
如果你得到终身职位?"
And they said, "Ecstatic!
他们说"喜出望外
This is something I've working on for many years
这是我多年努力的目标
and this will be it.
这将会是
This will be a dream come true."
将是梦想成真"
And-- "How happy are you going to stay for?"
"你会快乐多久?"
And they said, "For the rest of our lives.
他们说"余生都会很快乐
Because this is something we've been working for very long time.
因为这是我们努力很久的目标
It will make everything so much easier.
它会让一切变得更简单
I can get off the publish-or-perish race.
我可以停止不成功便成仁的竞争
I can enjoy my work much more.
我可以更加享受工作
This is going to transform my life."
这将改变我的人生"
And he asked them, "What happens if you don't get tenure?
他问他们"如果得不到终身职位会怎样?
If you are rejected?"
如果被拒绝呢?"
And they said, "We are going to be devastated.
他们说"我们会很难过
This is something we've been working for many, many years."
这是我们多年来努力的目标"
And-- "How long are you going to be devastated for?"
"那你们会痛苦多久?"
"Probably until we get tenure somewhere else.
"可能直到我们在别处获得终身职位
But even then, that may not be enough."--
即使到了那时 可能也不够"
Because once you don't get tenure in one place,
如果在一所学校无法获得终身职位
you don't go up in terms of the ranking of the school--
就没有可能在更高学府取得
you very often would get tenure but elsewhere,
经常是在别的院校获得
school that is not considered as good as the one
那些比拒绝你的学院
where you were rejected.
差一等的院校
So it will be devastating for a very long time.
所以那会让人难过很久
And Gilbert went to them at the moment
Gilbert再去访问他们
when they got the tenure decision.
这时他们已知道终身职位审核结果
Some of them got them. Others did not.
有些得到 有些没得到
"How are you feeling?" He asked.
他问"你们感觉如何?"
Those who got it,
得到的说
"Ecstatic! Happiest we've ever been."
"喜出望外 我们没从这样快乐过"
And-- "How long are you going to stay happy for?"
"你们的快乐会持续多久?"
"For the rest of our lives.
"余生都会倍感快乐
We've made it."
我们成功了"
And then he went to those who didn't get tenure and asked them,
然后他去找没得到终身职位的并问
"How are you feeling?"
"你们感觉如何?"
They were devastated.
他们很难过
And they were sure that
而且确信
they were going to remain devastated for a very long time.
会难过好久
And he went back to see them three months later,
三个月后 他再去访问他们
six months later.
六个月后再去
And what Gilbert and his colleagues found
Gilbert和他的同事发现
was that almost to the person,
几乎每一个人
those who got tenure or did not get tenure
不管得到还是没得到终身职位
went back to their previous level of well-being:
都恢复到之前的幸福水平
If they were happy before,
如果他们之前是快乐的
they were happy six months hence;
六个月后也是快乐的
if they were unhappy before,
如果他们之前是不快乐的
regardless whether they get tenure or not,
不管他们是否得到终身职位
they were not happy.
他们都是不快乐的
In other words, it looks like this and went back to base level or;
换言之 情形看似这样 然后回到基础水平
it looks like this and back to base level.
或者看似这样 然后回到基础水平
They did the same with lottery winners.
他们对中彩票的人做了同样的研究
"What if you really win ten million dollars,
"如果你真得中了一千万美元
will it actually make you happier?"
真得能让你更快乐吗?"
Yes-- for a while, but not for long.
是的 更快乐一段时间并不长久
Philip Brickman，Northwestern University did this research.
西北大学的Philip Brickman做了这个研究
After within 6 months,
经过六个月
people go back to their base level of wellbeing.
人们恢复基础的幸福水平
People in serious accidents with their paralysis
遇到严重意外的人
as the result of the accident,
意外导致瘫痪
very often, usually--
经常地 一般性的…
again, this is all the average--
再次强调 这是平均而言
go back to their base level of happiness:
都会恢复到基础幸福水平
if they are happy before,
他们以前是快乐的
they will be happy one year after;
一年后 他们也会快乐
if they are unhappy, they will remain unhappy.
如果不快乐 将维持不快乐
Extreme circumstances make very little difference to our wellbeing.
极端情况对我们的幸福影响很小
University of Illinois professor Ed Diener
伊利诺伊大学教授Ed Diener
does a lot of research on happiness levels.
就快乐水平作了大量研究
He has been doing it since the 1970s.
他自70年代开始研究
What he shows--
他的研究显示…
he and others including Daniel Kahneman, Nobel prize winner--
他和其他人 包括诺奖得主Daniel Kahneman
show is that wealth matters very little to our levels of wellbeing.
表明财富对幸福水平的影响很小
Just like the lottery
就像中了彩票
would make a very little difference to our wellbeing.
对我们是否幸福影响甚微
Now this does not mean that a person who doesn't have enough food,
并不是说一个没有足够食物
someone who is homeless on the streets here,
一个无家可归 流落街头的人
gets an extra thousand or two thousand dollars a month--
每个月多有一两千美元
that of course will make him or her much happier.
那当然会让他或她更快乐
But beyond the basic needs,
但超出基本需要后
once our basic needs are met and that means food,
当我们的基本需要得到满足 即有食物
shelter, basic education.
住所 基础教育
Once those needs are met,
这些需要一旦得到满足
income makes very little difference.
收入的影响就微乎其微
No change across generations.
几代人之间没有变化
Our generation is much wealthier than our parents,
我们这一代比父辈富足
much, much wealthier than our grandparents' generation.
比祖父辈更加富足
We are not happier.
我们不是更快乐
And that is global--
这是全球现象
whether it's China, whether it's in the UK or Australia,
不论是中国 英国还是澳大利亚
or the United States.
或美国
Levels of happiness are essentially static;
幸福水平几乎是静止的
and anxiety levels and depression levels,
焦虑水平和抑郁水平
as we talked about in the first class have gone up significantly.
正如第一堂课讲到的 有明显的加深
So income levels make very little difference.
收入水平的影响很小
In general, external circumstances make very little difference.
总得来说 外部环境的影响很小
I mean, think about your own experience:
回想你们的亲身经验
how did you feel--
你们感觉如何
go back, just transport yourself
回想自己
to experience of getting into Harvard,
考入哈佛时的体会
getting this big package in the mail which said "You were accepted"
信箱里收到一个大包写着"已录取"
on April 1 or the end of December,
在4月1日或12月未
when you got this pack--
当你拿到大包时
how did you feel? Probably ecstatic.
有何感受? 可能是喜出望外
Probably one of your highlights.
可能是你人生的亮点
And that moment, if you are like me,
在那一刻 如果你们像我一样
you thought, "This is it.
你们也会想"成功了
I'm really going to be happy for a very long time.
我会快乐很长一段时间
Cos I really struggled in high school--
因为我在高中很努力
a lot of it was difficult;
很多时很困难
a lot of it was painful, but it was all worth it.
很多时很痛苦 但完全值得
I made it."
我考上了哈佛"
And you went along with that feeling the next day,
第二天 你还会有这种感觉
because in school they started to talk about how you got in.
因为学校的人开始谈论你如何考上
And you felt fantastic about it, right?
你感觉很棒 不是吗?
And you felt great probably for the rest of the senior year--
可能整个高三都会感觉很棒
I mean, still ups and downs;
当然难免起起落落
but overall, high levels of happiness.
但总是来说是高水平的快乐
And it was going to last for the rest of your life.
这种快乐将持续一生
And you came here-- Freshmen week,
来到这里 经过新生周
you knew it was going to last for the rest of your life.
你知道快乐会持续一生
Because you were around wonderful people.
因为身边都是杰出的人
It was fun. There were parties.
大学生活很丰富 派对不断
And you said, "Everything they said about Harvard was not true.
你说"人们对哈佛的想法都错了
It's actually a party school."
这里其实是个派对大学"
You were certain of that, right?
你们很确定这一点 不是吗?
And not only was it a party school,
不仅是个派对大学
you were going to have an amazing time for the four years and beyond.
而且未来四年甚至以后 都会过得很快乐
Because your life was transformed by this letter of acceptance,
因为你的人生被这封录取信改变
right?
没错吧?
Things started to change probably on the first day of class,
事情也许从开课第一天就发生变化
but not entirely--
但没有完全不同
because there's shopping period and it's such a wonderful thing--
因为这是购物期 妙不可言的阶段
you shop for classes.
你们选择课程
It's even better than going to the mall--
比去商场更过瘾
so many, 3000 classes to choose from.
有三千门课程任你挑选
And this second week of Harvard is fantastic
在哈佛的第二周妙不可言
and it was going to continue just that way,
这种情况将持续下去
constant tide for the rest of your life.
余生将是一浪高于一浪的快乐
And then suddenly things begin to change.
事情突然开始发生变化
Slightly. Ever so slightly.
轻微地 非常轻微地
And they completely change once your first paper is due
要写第一篇论文时 情况彻底改变
or the midterms arrive.
或期中考试来临时
And you go back to your base level of wellbeing.
你恢复基础幸福水平
If you experience a lot of stress
如果你在高中
in high school and elementary school and were unhappy,
初中时经历过很大压力而且不快乐
generally the best predictor would say that
一般来说最好的预言家会说
you would feel the same way a month into your Harvard experience.
在哈佛呆上一个月 你会有同样的感觉
External circumstances matter very little. Very little.
外部环境影响甚微
In fact, also, place of residents makes very little difference.
同样地 居住地的影响也很小
People think, " Well, if I move--
人们会想"如果我搬到
especially in the day-light--
尤其是在白天
if I move to California, I'll be happier, right?" Wrong.
要是搬去加州 我会更快乐?" 错误
Californians are no happier than people in Massachusetts.
加州人不比麻省人更快乐
Initially when we go to a warm place,
刚去到一个温暖的地方
we feel the relief and there's this spiky level of wellbeing.
会感到放松 幸福水平高到值峰
But very quickly we go back to our base level
但很快我们会恢复基础水平
exactly where we were before.
和以前的我们一模一样
I'll take this even a step further,
我会进一步说明
even though there is no research about this,
虽然还没有这方面的研究
I bet you this is correct:
我敢和你们打赌 下面的说法是正确的
there is no difference in our levels of wellbeing
我们的幸福水平不会有所不同
if our place of residents is by the river
不论我们是生活在河边
or in the quad.
还是呆在quad （哈佛举行毕业典礼等重大集会的地方）
This is really taking the theory far, but it's true.
这个例子把理论推至极限 但是真的
I love this T-shirt-- what?
我喜欢这件衬衫 什么?
If you can't run with the big dogs, stay in yard.
不能和大狗一起跑就呆在院子里
Anyone from Korea here? Alright.
这里有韩国学生吗?好的
You made it all the way on such a cold day.
你在这么冷的日子赶来
Well done! I appreciated it.
很出色 我很感激
How spoiled we get here. Makes very little difference.
我们真是受宠若惊 不会有所不同
Very little difference--
微乎甚微的区别
where we are, where we live,
我们在哪里 我们生活在哪里
income levels, lottery, tenure,
收入水平 是否中彩票 是否取得终身职位
getting into our dream college,
入读理想中大学
getting our dream job for you seniors--
找到理想工作 大四学生
you may have just gotten it.
可能已经找到
Yeah, you are going to have a spike in your level of wellbeing--
没错 你们会感觉极至的幸福
I'm sure you had a spike in your level of wellbeing
我肯定拿到录取信时
when you got this acceptance letter,
你们的幸福感也达到峰值
but very quickly we go back to our base level.
但很快又恢复到基础水平
One thing that does matter to our base level of wellbeing
对基础幸福水平很重要的一样东西
which is external circumstance is democracy versus oppression.
它是一个外在因素 那就是民主和压迫
People living in democracies are generally significantly
生活在民主制度下的人通常明显
happier than people living in dictatorships.
比生活在独裁制度下的人更快乐
Women, for example,
以女性为例
living in places where they are oppressed are in general
生活在压迫制度下的一般
less happy than women living in free countries.
没有生活在自由国家的女性快乐
People living in Darfur are certainly
生活在达尔福尔的人
less happy than people living in Denmark or the United States.
肯定没有生活在丹麦或美国的人快乐
But again, these are the extreme circumstance
这些是能产生区别的
that do make a difference,
极端情况
such as I said, a homeless person,
比如我举的无家可归者的例子
of course, income will make a difference to that person.
收入当然会改善他的境遇
Moving to a free country,
移民到自由国家
of course, will make a difference to their wellbeing.
当然会让他们更加幸福
But beyond the extremes,
但在这些极端情况之外
additions or subtractions to our external circumstances
增加或减少的外部环境
make very little difference.
产生的区别很小
Now this is good news and bad news.
这即是好消息也是坏消息
The bad news is it seems like whatever we do,
坏消息是 看来不论我们怎么做
it doesn't matter.
都无关紧要
So why am I working hard in order to get that BCG job?
我为什么还要努力争取好工作？
why did I work so hard in order to get into this place?
我为什么要拼命入读这所学校
If it doesn't matter, if I experience this ups and downs.
如果这些都无关紧要 总要经历高低潮?
And the answer is that--
答案是
yes it won't make a difference to our wellbeing
是的 它不会改变我们的幸福水平
but it also doesn't mean that
但并不意味着
we cannot increase our level of wellbeing.
我们不能提升自己的幸福水平
Many people said the problem
很多人说
with general levels of happiness or unhappiness rather,
一般的快乐或不快乐水平
the cause is people have too high expectations.
是由于人们有过高的期望
And if we lower our expectations,
如果能降低期望
we lower our stress levels and we will enjoy life more.
降低压力水平 我们会更享受生活
"Ok, so I don't care if I don't get a B in the course.
我不在乎成绩是不是B
I'd be much happier if I don't care,
不在乎会让我更快乐
if I lower my levels of expectation.
如果我降低期望水平
I don't care what I get into, what job I have,
我不在乎从事什么工作
I just want to be happy."
只想快乐
And you'll probably be happy.
你可能会快乐
Slightly happy if you lower your levels of expectations,
降低期望水平会略微快乐些
but not in the long term.
但从长远来说行不通
And we'll talk about it next week.
下周我们会谈到这个问题
Not in the long term.
长远来说行不通
The problem is not lower these high expectations--
问题不在于是否降低那些高的期望
that doesn't matter.
这一点不重要
The problem is right versus wrong expectations.
问题在于正确和错误的期望
Not lower high expectations--
而不是低的和高的期望
that won't make a difference to our levels of wellbeing.
那不会影响我们的幸福水平
What will make a difference to our levels of wellbeing
能影响幸福水平的
is if we have right vs. wrong expectations.
是我们的期望是正确还是错误
It is wrong expectation to expect that getting into a certain place,
错误的期望认为进入某间公司
getting a raise,
获得升职
finding our dream partner,
找到理想的伴侣
is responsible for our happiness.
就能让自己更快乐
Moving to California or to (Forts Heimer?).
搬去加州或哈默堡
That in and of itself will not make us happier.
这本身不会让我们更快乐
That's wrong expectation.
那是错误的期望
The right expectation is to believe in change from within.
正确的期望是相信内在的改变
So these things will not make us happy.
这些事情不会让我们快乐
In fact, our readiness and potential to experience happiness
事实上 我们的准备和体验幸福的可能性
is mostly depended on our state of mind,
主要由我们的心境决定
not on our status, or the states of our bank account.
不是我们的地位或银行账户状况
It's about changing our perception-- state of mind.
我们要改变我们的认知 心境
It's about changing our interpretation of the world,
要改变我们对世界的诠释
of what's happening to us, of our achievements, of our failures.
以及我们的遭遇 成就 失败
It's about what we choose to perceive,
重要的是我们选择领悟什么
what we choose to focus on.
精力集中的焦点是什么
It's about transformation,
重要的是转变
as opposed to the external information or the external success.
而不是外部信息或外部成功
1504-- this whole course,
1504这门课程的重点
is about this transformation,
是关于转变
as I mentioned during the first lesson.
正如我在第一课中提到的
I want to move on to the fourth premise,
我想进入第四个前提
one of the most important premises in this course.
这堂课最重要的一个前提
And in many ways,
在很多方面
we can understand human intellectual history
我们能理解人类智力发展历史
just based on this idea:
仅仅基于这个观点
should we accept human nature?
应不应该接受人类本性?
Or can we perfect it?
我们能否完善它?
And can it change?
它能否改变?
This work relies on--
这个工作或者说这些观点
or these ideas rely on the work of Thomas Sowell.
基于Thomas Sowell的成果
Thomas Sowell, Harvard class of 58,
Thomas Sowell 哈佛58届学生
now at Stanford, the Hoover Institute,
目前就职斯坦福的胡佛研究院
one of my intellectual heroes.
我心中的一位知识分子英雄
And what he does and what his work does is basically explain
他的工作和作品的贡献在于解释了
why people choose to back one political party versus the other;
人们为什么会选择一个党派反对另一个
why they choose to live one kind of life versus the other.
为什么会选择一种生活方式摒弃另一种
This single book helped me understand myself better
这本书帮助我更好地了解自己
as well as other people better--
更好地了解别人
whether it's politically,
不论是政治上
whether it's psychologically, whether it's philosophically.
心理上还是哲学观上
Those of you who are interested in politics
对政治感兴趣的同学
and there is one book you want to read,
如果说有一本书是必读的
after you read Marva Collins of course, it's this.
读完Marva Collins的作品后 就是这本
So what does Thomas Sowell say?
Thomas Sowell所执的观点是什么？
Essentially what he does is divide people into two camps
他把人分成两个阵营
those who hold constrained vision,
那些认为本性受约束
the limited vision;
有局限性的观点的人
and those who hold the unconstrained,
和认为人性不受约束
the unlimited vision of human nature.
无局限性的观点的人
People who hold constrained vision of human nature,
认为人性受约束的观点的人
believe that human nature cannot be changed;
相信人性无法改变
it's immutable-- we have certain instincts,
它是永恒的 我们有一些本能
we have certain inclinations.
有一些欲望
They are fixed. This is it.
它们是固有的 无法改变
What you see is what you get.
是什么样就是什么样
What you are born with or were born with,
作为人的物种
as species, is all we have.
只有与生俱来的东西
The flaws that are out there are inevitable--
我们的缺陷不可避免
they cannot be changed.
无法改变
We need to accept them for what they are.
不论好坏 我们只能接受
That's the only thing we can do with these flaws.
我们只能接受缺陷
And people who have the constrained vision think
执有人性受约束的观点的人认为
that our instincts, our inclinations,
我们的本能 欲望
our basic nature is immutable, accepted.
我们的本性是永恒的 唯有接受
And then what they do, rather than resign, they channel it.
但他们没有屈服 而是加以引导
How do they channel it?
如何引导?
By building certain political institutions
通过建立某种政治机构
that would channel the flawed,
引导有缺陷的
imperfect human nature toward the good.
不完美的人性向好的方面发展
Philosophers and psychologists
执有这种观点的
who fall under the constrained vision create them,
哲学家和心理学家创造了它们
philosophies and psychologies and institutions and systems
创建了人生哲学 心理学 各种机构和体系
to channel our flawed and imperfect nature.
来引导我们有缺点的不完美的人性
People who fall under the constrained vision in the history of ideas,
在哲学史上认为人性受约束的人
are people such as Alexander Hamilton, Adam Smith--
包括汉密尔顿 亚当斯密
those of you are taking or will take EC 10,
学习经济学的都耳熟能详
?, Fredrick Kayak.
Fredrick Kayak等
These are people who say,
这些人认为
"our nature is constrained.
"我们的本性是受约束的
It's limited." Edmund Burke-- another one.
是有局限的" Edmund Burke说的
What captures this idea best--
最准确阐述这种观点的
the words of Francis Bacon,
是培根的话
considered the father of the scientific movement,
他是17世纪时科学运动之父
was a philosopher in 1600s:
是一名哲学家
"Nature to be commanded must be obeyed."
"号令自然 必须遵守自然"
Whether it's physical nature, or human nature.
不论是物质本质还是人性本质
We need to obey it.
我们都需要遵守它
It is what it is.
本质是不变的
Now we have the unconstrained vision.
还有人性不受约束的观点
Perhaps you are a little bit more optimistic,
也许你更乐观
a little bit more utopian-- human nature can be improved.
更加乐天 人性可以改善
It can be changed.
可以改变
It is up to us to do so. It is perfectable.
取决于我们去不去做 本性可以完善
We don't need to accept these flaws as inevitable.
不需要接受缺陷不可避免的观点
We can perfect it.
可以完善它
There are solutions to these flaws,
有办法解决这些缺陷
to these imperfections and our role--
完善不完美的地方 我们的职责
the goal of institutions,
机构的目标
whether it's political institutions,
不论是政治机构
educational institutions, of systems,
教育机构 各种体系
organizations, individual philosophers, psychologists,
各种组织 个体哲学家 心理学家
the role is to change our nature,
职责都是改变人类本性
to perfect it, to better it.
完善它 把它变得更好
Philosophers who help this position:
致力于此的哲学家
people like Thomas Jefferson,
有托马斯杰斐逊
people like Jean-Jacques Rousseau,
卢梭
George Bernard Shaw, Ronald Dworkin and other leading thinkers.
萧伯纳 德沃金及其他杰出思想家
And what Thomas Sowell did
Thomas Sowell的贡献是
was map the entire intellectual history
绘制了整个世界智力发展历史
of world showing how people who held this view versus that view,
展示出人们执有不同观点
that two radically different political prescriptions.
两种截然不同的政治观点
The person who best captures the unconstrained view,
最好地阐述了本性受约束观点的人
Benjamin Constant, French philosopher and politician,
法国哲学家政治家Benjamin Constant说
"It is for self-perfectioning that destiny calls us."
"命运召唤我们进行自我完善"
Generally people on constrained view,
执本性受约束观点的人
are people politically, not always,
是在政治上 并非总是
but usually people who would support capitalism--
但一般都是支持资本主义的人
people like Adam Smith,
比如亚当斯密
who talked about "invisible hand"--
开创了"不可见的手"的理论
Let's channel imperfect, perhaps flawed human nature toward the good.
把不完美 有缺陷的本性导向好的
People who are more on the unconstrained vision
执本性不受约束观点的人
would tend toward Utopianism or sometimes communism.
倾向乌托邦主义或共产主义
Not always, but sometimes.
并非总是 有时是
Why? Because let's change human nature.
为什么？让我们来改变人类本性
Self-interest is not good.
自利不是好事
It hurts in the long term and therefore,
长远来说是有害的 所以
we need to change it rather than the constrained vision--
我们需要改变它 而认为本性受约束的人
people who said,
他们会说
"We may not like it, but it is what it is.
"我们也许不是那样 但本性难移
We cannot change it.
不能改变它
Let's make the best of it and channel it toward the good."
我们尽去完善它 把它导向好的"
Two radical views.
两种皆然不同的观点
Two radical prescriptions based on people's notion perspective.
基于人的观念得到两种皆然不同的手段
So why am I telling you this?
我为什么要给你们讲这个?
This is not a political science class.
这不是政治科学课程
Because it has every relevance to psychology as well.
因为它与心理学息息相关
It has every relevance to psychology:
它与心理学息息相关
Do we perceive reality,
我们认识了现实吗
human nature as constrained or unconstrained
对人类本性执不同观点
will ultimately affect our psychology.
最终将影响我们心理
And this is very meaningful and important.
这是非常有意义和重要的
Let me explain.
我来解释
Now first of all,
首先
some people who have the constrained view when it comes to politics,
有些人在政治上执受约束的观点
have the unconstrained view when it comes to psychology,
但在心理学上执不受约束观点
so it is not always consistent,
并不总是一致
though it very often is.
但多数时是一致的
So the vision of psychology this course promotes
这门课提倡的心理学观点
is the constrained view.
是本性受约束观点
In other words, my belief--
换言之 那是我相信的观点
and I am going to back that up with research today
我会用三个研究加以证明 从今天开始
and for the next semester--
直到下个学期
is human nature is fixed.
人类本性是固有的
We have inclinations.
我们有欲望
We have certain instincts that are there
我们有生而有之的本能
and have been formed either God-given or evolutionary-given
或上天赐与或经几百万年
for millions of years that have been formed.
在进化中形成
They are not going to change any time soon.
这些本性不会很快改变
Not in our life time.
在有生之年是不可能的
It's fixed.
它是固有的
We are stuck with them through good and ill.
不论好坏 我们都要接受它们
And all we can do after we accept this nature
在接受这个本性后 我们唯一能做的
is to first understand it through research,
是通过研究首先来理解它
and then after we understand it,
理解它后
make the best use of it.
好好地利用它
Understand it through research as well as through the search--
通过研究 探究
through introspection,
通过内省来理解它
and then make the best use of it.
然后好好地利用
How can I channel my nature?
如何引导我的本性?
And what I want to do now is illustrate a case study
现在我想演示一个案例研究
of what I mean by nature constrained
说明我所谓的本性受约束的含义
and why it is so important for happiness,
为何它对快乐
for wellbeing, for long-term success
幸福 长久的成功如此重要
to have the constrained view of human nature
当论及到我们的心理时
when it comes to our psychology that is.
人性受约束观点很重要
The topic I want to talk about is the permission to be human.
我谈及的话题是准许为人
I am going to talk about this topic for three reasons.
原因有三
A, because it illustrates what Thomas Sowell means
第一 它说明了Thomas Sowell的观点
politically in the psychological realm.
在心理学领域的政治方面
Second, because I think it is one of
第二 因为我认为它是
the most important pillars of wellbeing and happiness.
快乐和幸福的最重要支柱之一
The third reason why I want to talk about it is
第三个原因
because it gets to misunderstanding that many people have
因为它引起人们
regarding what positive psychology is and is not.
对何为积极心理学的误解
When I first started teaching this course
当我开始教授这门课时
and had six students,
有六名学生
I remember one day sitting in Leverett House,
我记得有一天坐在学生宿舍里
having lunch by myself and one of the students comes in and says,
独自用餐 一名学生走进来说
"can I join you?" "Sure." we have lunch.
"能一起吃吗?""当然" 我们共进午餐
And he says to me,
他对我说
"Tal, I hear you teaching a class on happiness."
"Tal 我听说你教一门有关快乐的课程"
And I said to him, "Yes. That's right."
我对他说"是的 没错"
And he said, "You know, my roommates are taking your class."
他说"我的室友选了你的课"
And I said, "That's wonderful."
我说"那太好了"
There were two of the six.
六名学生中有了两名
And he said, "But Tal, you've got to watch out now."
他说"Tal 你现在要多加小心"
And I said to him, "Why?"
我问"为什么?"
And he said, "Tal, you'll have to be careful."
他说"Tal 你必须小心"
And I said, "Why?"
我说"为什么?"
And he said, "Because if I see you unhappy,
他说"因为如果我见到你不快乐
I'll tell them."
我会告诉他们"
The next day in class,
第二天上课时
I used that and I said to the students,
我讲了这件事并对学生说
"You know, the last thing in the world that I want you to think
"我最不希望你们以为
is that I experience a constant high or that you,
我总是保持快乐 或者你们
by the end of the semester or the year--
在期未或学年未
it was a year course,
那门课程要讲一年
you-- by the end of the year--
你们到学年未时
will experience a constant high."
会一直保持快乐"
There are two kinds of people,
只有两类人
who experience this constant high,
体会这种持续的快乐
who don't experience painful emotions such as anger,
不会体会到痛苦的情绪 像愤怒
or envy, or disappointment,
嫉妒 失望
or sadness, or unhappiness,
悲伤 不快乐
or depression, or anxiety at times--
抑郁或偶尔的焦虑
two kinds of people who don't experience these painful emotions:
两类人不会体会到这些痛苦的情绪
the one kind are the psychopaths--
一类是精神病人
by definition they don't experience these painful emotions;
因此不会感受到痛苦的情绪
the second kind of people
第二类
who don't experience these painful emotions are dead people.
没有痛苦情绪体会的 是死人
Exactly! So you know,
没错 所以
if you experience these emotions,
如果你们体会到这些情绪
it's a good sign.
那是个好兆头
You are not a psychopath, and you are alive.
说明你不是精神病人 也还没死
However, in our culture today,
然而在当今的文化中
we don't give ourselves the permission to be human,
我们不准许自己为人
the freedom to experience these painful emotions as well.
也没有体会痛苦情绪的自由
And we pay a very high price for this inability,
我们为这种无能付出高昂代价
for this refusal to accept the fact
为拒绝接受
that it is part of human nature that is constrained,
本性受约束
that is there no matter what.
生而有之的事实 付出高昂代价
As kids, as babies--
孩子和婴儿
going back to the baby's scene,
回到婴儿期
we give ourselves the permission to be human,
我们准许自己为人
we know that it's natural.
我们知道那是自然的
We don't even think about it in fact,
事实上根本不去思考
to experience the high and then the low and high and then low.
自然而然地经历起起落落
And later on, when we stop giving ourselves the permission
后来当我们停止准许自己为人时
to be human when the facade become so important,
当我们的“面子”变得重要起来的时候
we begin to realize that other people are watching us
当我们开始发觉其他人在看我们时
and evaluating us constantly
时刻评价我们时
and we think they do so much more than they actually do.
人们远没我们以为的那么注意我们
That's when we stop giving ourselves the permission to be human,
那时我们停止准许自己为人
and we pay a price, in terms of our energy levels,
为此我们付出代价 包括精力水平
of our wellbeing, of our happiness,
幸福感 快乐感
of our creativity, and ultimately also our success.
创造力 最终以成就大小作为代价
Let me give an example of someone
我举一个
who does give himself the permission to be human.
准许自己为人的例子
The Permission to be Human
准许为人
Now I'm saying we should look like this.
不是说大家应该像那样
But what I am saying is that we all need a space,
我的意思是我们都需要一个空间
a place in our own lives
生活中要有一个地方
where we give ourselves the permission to be human,
在那里我们准许自己为人
whether it's with close friends,
可以是和挚友在一起时
people we care about,
我们关心的人
whether it's first and foremost with ourselves
最重要的是面对自己时
when we write a journal,
写日记时
where we do give ourselves the permission to be,
这时我们准许自己为人
to cry, to be joyous--
准许自己哭泣 快乐
because if we don't,
如果不那么做
we pay a price.
我们付出代价
We need a space of unconditional acceptance.
我们需要一个无条件接受自我的地方
The best advice that I got,
我得到的最好建议
or that we got--
或者说是我们
my wife and I got when David,
是我妻子和我 当David
our first son was born from our pediatrician, Dr. Tok Shapiro--
我们的大儿子出生时 Tok Shapiro医生给的
and David was born at 1 AM in the morning
David在凌晨一点出生
and around 8 AM in the morning,
早上八点时
he came in to see, to check up on my wife,
他来查看我妻子的情况
to check up on the baby,
查看婴儿的情况
for some reason, he didn't check up on me.
不知为什么 他没询问我的情况
And everything was fine.
一切都正常
As he is leaving the room,
在他走出房间时
he turned around and said,
他转过身说
" Just one more thing.
"还有一件事
over the next few months,
在接下来的几个月里
you are going to be experiencing every single kind of emotion
你们将体会到每一种情绪
to the extreme and that's fine.
极至的情绪 那没关系
It's natural.
是很自然的事
We all go through it."
我们都经历过"
And he walked out.
然后他走了出去
It was the best advice
这是妻子和我
that my wife and I got regarding child-rearing.
得到的关于抚育孩子的最好建议
Why? Let me give you an example.
为什么？让我举个例子
So after about a month,
一个月后
I started to, once in a while,
我开始偶尔
experience some envy toward David.
对David产生一种嫉妒
Because here he was for the first time in--
因为这是妻子和我在一起后
well, since my wife and I were together--
第一次有人夹在中间
someone else is getting much more attention than I was,
另一个人比我获得更多的关注
no matter how much I cried.
不管我怎么哭
And I felt envy toward him and five minutes later,
我嫉妒他 然后五分钟后
I experienced this most intense love toward him--
我对他产生最强烈的爱意
the emotion that I haven't felt before.
一种我从没感受过的情绪
Now normally I would think,
平时我会想
"what a hypocritic!
"真是个伪君子
It's just something is wrong:
事情不对劲
one minute you are envious and the next minute you experience love?"
前一分钟充满嫉妒 转眼体会无尽爱意?"
There is nothing wrong.
这完全合情合理
There is everything right.
完全正确
It's part of being human.
这是为人的一部分
And because I had Dr.Shapiro's voice at back of my mind--
因为我脑子里装着儿科医生的建议
permission to be human,
准许为人
that helped me a great deal--
那帮了我很多
experience the envy when I experienced it, accept it;
我体会嫉妒 接受它
and then enjoy and celebrate it--
然后享受和赞美
the positive emotions that I experienced toward David.
我对David产生的积极情绪
Permission to be human.
准许为人
You see, there is actually a paradox playing--
这里有自相矛盾的地方
this is work done by our very own Daniel Wegner on ironic processing.
Daniel Wegner对"反语处理"做过研究
When we suppress a natural phenomenon,
当我们压抑一种自然现象时
that phenomenon only strengthens.
那种现象只会加强
Let me illustrate through an experiment.
我用一个实验加以说明
So for the next ten seconds,
在接下来的十秒钟里
do not think of a pink elephant.
不要想粉色大象
For the next ten seconds, do not think of a pink elephant.
在接下来的十秒钟里不要想粉色大象
You know the one that I am talking about?
知道我说的是什么吗？
With the big ears, Dumbo?
就是大耳朵的小飞象?
Do not think of a pink elephant for the next three seconds
在接下来的十秒钟里不要想粉色大象
and I am sure no one thought of a pink elephant right?
我肯定没有人想一头粉色大象 是吗?
What happened? -- Most people thought of a pink elephant.
事实如何?多数人都会想粉色大象
Because when we try to suppress a natural phenomenon
因为当我们企图压抑一种自然现象时
such as having a visual of the word when we say it,
比如提起一个词时浮现出相应形象
that thing just intensifies.
只会加强它
The same applies to the painful emotions that are natural.
压抑自然的痛苦情绪也有此效果
And when we try to suppress them, they strengthen.
企图压制它们时 它们会加强
When I started to teach after hearing about
当我听说Marva Collins的事迹
Marva Collins and deciding teaching is my calling,
并决定以教书为终身职业时
I knew that I had to deal with the problem--
我知道必须克服一个问题
the problem is that I am introvert,
那就是我个性内性
I get very nervous in front of audiences and large audiences for me
站在听众前面我会很紧张 对我来说
is anything but five.
超过五个人就算众多听众
But I had to deal with it
但我必须克服这个问题
and I knew I would have to deal with it.
我知道必须克服它
So I would go on in front of audience and before
所以我会站在听众面前 在那之前
that I would say to myself,
我会对自己说
"Tal, don't be nervous.
"不要紧张
Don't be anxious.
不要焦虑
No anxiety today.
今天不能焦虑
Don't be nervous.
不要紧张
Don't be nervous. Don't!"
不要紧张 不要"
And what happened?--
事实又是怎样?
Pink elephants all around.
我即紧张又焦虑
Instead after especially reading
但在读过 Victor Frankl
about paradoxical intentions by Victor Frankl,
有关"矛盾意向"的阐述后
I started to give myself the permission to be human.
我开始准许自己为人
And now when I go into a lecture, the nervousness--
现在当我去上课时 紧张感
because I give myself the permission to be human--
因为我准许自己为人
goes away within as little as three hours into the lecture.
在课堂进行三小时后会消失
But no, it's manageable.
但紧张是可以控制的
I still get nervous before every single lecture,
每次上课前 我仍会感觉紧张
which is actually a good thing. But it's managable.
其实这是件好事 它可以控制
I can deal with it. I can handle it.
我能应付它 能控制它
Permission to be human.
准许为人
You see, rejecting our nature leads to suboptimal performance
拒绝本性导致次优表现
emotionally as well as in terms of external performance.
不论在情绪上还是外在表现
Imagine waking up every morning and saying to yourself:
想象每天早上醒来后对自己说
"I refuse to accept the law of gravity.
"我拒绝接受万有引力定律
This law of gravity is such a pain.
万有引力定律很麻烦
You need to walk down the stairs and then up the stairs.
要被迫上下楼
I just want to float to Sanders (Sanders Theatre) in the morning.
我只想早上时飘去剧院
I just want to float to the dining hall after--
我只想下午时飘去餐厅
so much easier, so much less painful."
更加容易 更少痛苦"
Imagine leading a life like this.
想象过这样一种生活
Will you truly refuse to accept the law of gravity?
你真的能拒绝接受万有引力定律吗?
What kind of life would you lead?
那会是怎么一样生活?
Well, first of all, you may not survive for long,
首先 你可能活不长
if you truly don't accept the fact that things,
如果你不接受
people being no exception fall when left in mid-air.
人会从半空中掉下来的事实
But even if you do survive--
即使你幸存下来
let's the ground floor--
比如你在一楼
even if you do survive,
就算你真的幸存下来
you would lead a life of constant frustration--
你的生活将是处处受挫
refusing to accept something that is there
拒绝接受现实事物
whether you like it or not.
不论你喜欢与否
So instead we accept the law of gravity.
所以我们接受万有引力定律
More than that, we create games around the law of gravity.
不仅如此 我们利用定律发明游戏
I mean all those of you doing sports here--
你们中喜欢运动的
and it's most of you in this room who are doing athletics,
教室里多数人都做运动
who go for a run, you rely on the law of gravity.
跑步时需要万有引力定律
Can you imagine
你能想象哈佛和耶鲁
Harvard vs. Yale football without the law of gravity?
在没有万有引力的情况下进行橄榄球赛吗?
Can you imagine a basketball game without the law of gravity?
你能想象没有万有引力情况下的篮球赛吗?
I am not talking about Michael Jordan, but for the (?).
我不是在说乔丹 而是普通人
We accept it and we create games around it.
我们接受它 并利用它发明游戏
And yet we don't do the same when it comes to our emotions.
然而说到情绪时 我们却不这么做
Now here is the key point:
这是关键点
Painful emotions are as much as part of human nature
人类本性的痛苦情绪
as the law of gravity is part of physical nature.
一如物理世界的万有引力定律
And "nature to be commanded must be obeyed".
"号令自然 必须遵守自然"
And the aeronautics engineer
航空航天工程师
who wants to build an airplane has to obey,
想制造飞机 必须遵守
take into consideration, learn it,
加以考虑 学习
study and understand the law of gravity.
研究理解万有引力定律
The same applies to a psychologist.
心理学家也是如此
The constrained view of human nature.
人类本性受约束的观点
"Nature to be commanded must be obeyed."
号令自然 必须遵守自然
And yet we don't do that.
然而我们却不那么做
We don't do in our culture.
我们的文化不那么做
And we pay a high price for it.
为此我们付出高昂代价
We have what I called, "the great deception".
我们正在经历我所谓的"大骗局"
We are people who ask, "So how are you doing?"
我们是那种嘴上说"你好吗?"
And we say, "Fine. Just great."
嘴上说"很好 棒极了"
Well in fact, we are not doing so well.
事实上我们不是那么好
More appropriate would be "I'm going through a rough patch now.
更合适的回应是"我正经历不顺
I'm going through a hard time. I'm really stressed."
恰逢困境 我很难受"
But yet, we don't want to admit that.
然而我们不想承认事实
We don't give ourselves the permission to be human,
我们不准许自己为人
because we think there is something wrong with us
因为我们觉得是自己有毛病
if we experience these emotions.
如果我们有这样的情绪
And then when everyone says,
每个人都说
"Oh fine. Oh great. Oh terrific",
"很好 棒极了 妙不可言"
then we are asked "How are you doing?"
当我们被问到"你好吗?"时
I am not going to be the only party poop here.
我才不要作唯一的扫把星
I am not going to be the only depressed one around here.
我才不要作唯一的丧气鬼
So I said, "Oh fine. Oh great."
于是我说"很好 棒极了"
And then we contribute to this great deception
就这样我们帮忙壮大了这个大骗局
and it is this great deception that leads to the great depression--
正是这个大骗局导致严重的抑郁
the great depression in the ultimate currency of happiness.
严重的抑郁是快乐付出的终极代价
This, to great extent,
这很好地解释了
explains why so many people today
为什么今天有那么多人
experience depression the 45% figure,
感到抑郁 达到45%
nationwide on college campuses.
全国大学校园都如此
Not enough permission to be human.
没有足够的"准许为人"
I am not talking about wearing our heart on our sleeves.
我不是说要我们肆无忌惮地表达情绪
When someone comes to us
有人走向我们
in the elevator in William James (William James Hall),
在William James大厅的电梯里
I says, "How are you doing?"
我说"你好吗?"
"Thank you for asking.
"感谢关心
You know it all started when I was three."
这得从我三岁时说起"
This is not what I am talking about.
我不是这个意思
In William James, maybe the case--
在William James大厅也许会遇到这种事
because the elevator--
因为那部电梯
it does take two hours to get there for the door to close.
运作得太慢
But other than that.
但不是那样
I'm not talking about.
我不是那个意思
what I'm talking about is a space,
我的意思是一个空间
a safe space in our lives with our closest friends,
生活中的私密空间 和挚友一起时
with our family, first and foremost, with ourselves,
和家人在一起时 最重要的是面对自己时
will we have the permission to be human.
我们要准许自己为人
And what I'm not talking about is resignation.
我说的不是屈从
Far from it. It's not about saying,
远远不是那样 不是说
"Well I'm depressed. There's nothing I can do about it.
"我很抑郁 这是毫无办法的事
I accept my nature.
我接受我的本性
I accept my state.
接受我的状态
And that's it."
就这样吧"
I'm not talking about resignation.
我说的不是屈从
what I'm talking about is active acceptance.
我说的是主动接受
What does that mean?
那是什么意思?
It means understanding that certain things
它意味着理解有些事
I cannot change and certain things I can and ought to change.
我无法改变 有些事我能而且应该去改变
One of the main ideas we'll talk about is the distinction:
我们会集中讨论的一点是"差别"
we'll talk about specifically on the lecture on change
在有关"改变"的课上中会着重谈
between affect, behaviors and cognitions.
情感 行为和认知的差别
The A, B, C of psychology.
心理学的ABC
Affect-- emotion. Behavior-- action.
情感代表情绪 行为代表行动
Cognition-- thoughts.
认知代表思想
Unconditional acceptance,
无条件地接受
permission to be human relates primarily to our affect,
准许为人 主要与情感相关
to our emotions.
与情绪相关
They are there, just like the law of gravity is there.
它们是现实存在 就像万有引力定律
That does not mean we need to accept our behavior and our cognition.
那不代表我们要接受我们的行为和认知
For example, I can--
举个例子 我可以…
and having the past experience--
因为以前的经历
envy towards my best friend,
嫉妒我最好的朋友
that in and of itself does not make me a bad person.
那种情绪本身不代表我是个坏人
It's human.
这是人类本性
I've never met a person
我从没遇到过任何一个
who has never experienced or does not experience--
从来没有或没有体会过…
well, maybe the Dalai Lama--
也许达赖喇嘛可以
but other than that,
除了他
who does not experience envy toward other people.
谁都嫉妒过别人
And if it is true about the Dalai Lama,
如果说达赖喇嘛真的无欲无求
that is because he's worked on it for decades.
那也是修行几十年的结果
Envy is part of human nature--
嫉妒是人性的一部分
nothing good or bad about the envy.
嫉妒没有好坏之分
Nothing good or bad about experiencing the anger.
愤怒也无好坏之分
Nothing good or bad about experiencing the depression or anxiety.
抑郁和焦虑也无好坏之分
It's part of human nature.
那是人性的一部分
However, the question is,
问题在于
how do I choose to behave,
我要选择怎样的行为
to act as a result of it?
去表达情感？
That is where the moral domain enters.
道德在此介入
That's where I can have moral or immoral behavior
我可以选择道德和不道德的行为
toward my best friend or baby, or other people in general.
对待最好的朋友 孩子或一般人
I can still experience envy toward my best friend
我仍会嫉妒最好的朋友
and choose to behave generously and benevolently toward him.
但选择对他宽容和亲切
The same with cognition and we will talk a lot about it
认知也是如此 我们会深入讨论认知
when we talk about CBT-- Cognitive Behavioral Therapy.
当谈到认知行为治疗时
I can feel it certain way.
我可以感受它
But it doesn't mean that
但不代表
I need to resign to my thoughts about that feeling.
我要屈从于对那种感受的想法
Rumination is one of the things that we'll talk about a lot
我们会频繁谈到沉思
actually not that helpful--
其实沉思痛苦的情绪
to ruminate about painful emotions.
没有多大帮助
It's much helpful to write about them.
书写描述更有帮助
To talk to other people about them,
向别人倾诉更有帮助
rather than just be thinking constantly about
要胜过总是想着
how miserable I am because my girlfriend just left.
被女朋友甩了多么的惨
I haven't found anyone in Pinocchio's.
我还没在快餐店找到新目标
So rumination doesn't help.
沉思没有帮助
So I don't necessarily accept
我没有必要接受
all my irrational thoughts and again,
所有不理智的想法
we'll talk about it much more next week of
下周我们会更深入地探讨
how we can cognitively reframe what we were thinking.
如何认知性地重塑自己的想法
But the emotion-- that affect is the emotion,
但情绪 情感即情绪
it is what it is.
是无法改变的
And the key is to be true to reality,
重要的是要真实面对现实
which is also one of the main themes in the course.
这也是本门课的重要主题之一
In many ways, this course should not be called "Positive Psychology".
从很多方面来说这门课不该叫"积极心理学"
But I am telling you this after you already signed up for the class
我在你们选了这门课后才挑明
so it is too late to leave.
想退课也晚了
This is actually not a course on positive psychology.
这门课不是讲"积极心理学"
It's a course in reality psychology.
而是一门"现实心理学"课程
Because positive psychology may mean that
因为积极心理学可能表示
we are only focusing on the positive and what works,
我们只聚焦于积极的起作用的部分
ignoring all the rest that are not.
忽略其余不起作用的
Overdoing this class is shifting the pendulum.
我们要做的就像是改变钟摆幅度
So there is more even playing field instead of the 21:1 ratio,
比起21比1的比率 两方更均衡
we are doing much more, focusing on the positive.
我们做得更多 除了专注于积极的一面
And at the same time,
与此同时
accepting the painful emotions
也认同痛苦的情绪
are as much part of human nature as the wonderful emotions.
和美好的情绪一样都是人性的组成
And sooner we accept it, the better.
我们越早接受越好
That won't mean at the end of the course of 1504 or 100
那并不代表在1504课程结束后
or 100 other courses in the workshop
或修读完另外100门课程
and sold the books that you read,
然后就可以把读过的书丢了
it's not that you will not have painful emotions anymore.
并不是说 你就不会再感受到痛苦的情绪
It's simply your psychological immune system will become stronger,
只是你的心理免疫系统会变得更强
hopefully already by the end of this semester.
希望在本学期未就见成效
Psychological immune system will become stronger.
心理免疫系统会变得更强
And that means not that we don't get ill.
那不表示我们不再得病
It means we get ill less often and when we do get sick,
而是意味着我们更有抵抗力 即使得病
we'll recover more promptly.
也能很快康复
The difference between the extremely happy people
极其快乐的人和极其不快乐的人
and extremely unhappy people is not that one gets sad,
区别不是在于一个会伤心
of upset, or anxious, or depressed;
难过 焦虑或抑郁
and the other does not.
而另一个不会
Both groups do.
两类人都会
It's how quickly,
区别在于他们能够多么迅速
how promptly we can recover from these painful emotions--
多么快速地从痛苦情绪中恢复过来
in other words, how strong our psychological immune system is.
换言之 我们的心理免疫系统有多强
And our psychological immune system strengthens
我们的心理免疫系统会加强
when we give ourselves the permission to be human.
当我们准许自己为人时
Many of you've probably read this,
很多同学可能读到过这首诗
come across this, but I think this captures
听说过这首诗 它非常好地阐述了
so well the foundation of what it means to be actively accepting.
主动接受含义的基础
This has become the official mantra in many ways of the AA movement:
它已成为AA运动的正式圣言
"God, grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change;
"主啊 请赐我安详 接纳我不能改变的事物
the courage to change the things I can change;
请赐我勇气 去改变我可以改变的东西
and wisdom to know the difference."
并赐我智慧去认识这两者的差别"
The wisdom to know the difference--
认识两者差别的智慧
fortunately, a lot of this wisdom can come from studies,
幸运的是 这样的智慧可以通过学习获得
from research, from deep introspection that
通过研究和在这个学期
you will do throughout the semester.
进行的深刻反省中获得
What I want to do now is an exercise.
现在我想做个练习
I want to do a group meditation.
我想做一次群体冥想
Trying to understand,
希望你们理解
not just on the cognitive level of the research,
不只是在研究的认知层面上
but also to experience on the visceral emotional level,
还要在内心情感层面上去体会
what it really means to give ourselves the permission to be human.
准许自己为人的真正含义
Those of you who don't feel comfortable doing it,
感觉不自在的
you don't have to do it.
可以不参与
Those who feel comfortable to do it, do it.
认为没问题的 一起来做
If it's a stretch for you,
如果你觉得很勉强
I still recommend that you do it.
我仍建议你一起来
If you never meditate before,
如果你从没冥想过
this is a wonderful opportunity to do it for the first time.
这是你们尝试的好机会
One thing I do ask you:
我对你们的一个要求是
If you are not doing it,
如果你不做
if you don't participate,
不参与的同学
simply just keep quiet.
请保持安静
Other than that, I really do recommend that you join us.
此外 我强烈建议你参与
What I want to do together now
现在我要大家一起
is enter the realm of unconditional acceptance.
一起进入无条件接受境界
Se?or, just sit up straight as much as possible.
在座位上尽量坐直身体
If possible, your back relaxing against the back rest.
如果可以 后背在靠背上放松
Plant your feet comfortably on the floor.
双脚舒服地放在地板上
If you feel comfortable, close your eyes.
感觉舒适 闭上双眼
Shift the focus of your breath.
转移呼吸的焦点
Shift the focus of your thoughts to your breathing.
把思想的焦点 转移到呼吸上
Take a deep breath in all the way down to your belly.
向腹部深深吸气
And then breathe out.
然后呼气
Again, deep breath in;
再一次深深吸气
slow, gentle, quiet breath out.
缓慢 平稳 安静地呼气
Repeat that in silence.
安静地重复呼吸
If your mind wanders, simply bring it back to your breathing.
如果走神了 回到呼吸上
Deep, slow inhalation.
深深缓慢地吸气
Deep, slow, gentle, quiet exhalation.
深深缓慢 平稳 安静地呼气
Most of us don't breathe deeply enough.
多数人吸气的深度不够
We don't take the time to celebrate our breath,
我们没时间赞美我们的呼吸
our spirit, our being.
我们的精神 我们的存在
The connection, the link,
联系 关联
the bridge between our mind and our body;
心灵与身体的桥梁
between our emotions and our thoughts;
情绪和思想的桥梁
between the brain and the heart.
脑和心的桥梁
Continue with the deep breathing.
继续深呼吸
As you continue with the deep breath,
继续深呼吸的同时
shift your focus to your emotions, to your feelings.
将焦点转向情绪 转向感受
How are you doing?
你们好吗？
How are you feeling?
感觉如何？
Pay attention to your emotions.
注意你的情绪
Whatever they are, whatever it is that your feeling,
不论是怎样的情绪 不论感觉到什么
allow it to float through you. Naturally.
让它流过你的全身 自然地
Just experience your emotion whatever it is.
体会那种情绪
You may feel one emotion at one moment,
你可能先体会到一种情绪
different emotion the next. That's Ok.
然后又体会到另一种 这没关系
Whatever it is, accept it.
不论是怎么情绪 接受它
Experience it.
体会它
Give yourself the permission to be human.
准许自己为人
It's all OK. Just breath.
都没关系 呼吸
Continue to observe and experience whatever emotion comes up,
继续观察体会出现的情绪
whether it's calm or happiness,
不管是平静或快乐
whether it's anxiety, confusion, boredom or joy.
不管是焦虑 困惑 无聊或喜悦
Whatever it is,
不管它是什么
continue to breathe deeply into your belly.
继续向腹部深呼吸
And gently, slowly, quietly exhale.
平稳 缓慢 安静地呼气
Let the emotion flow just like the breath.
让那种情绪像呼吸一样流动
As you continue breathing deeply,
随着呼吸的加深
in your mind's eye,
用你的心眼
see yourself walking out of this classroom today,
看自己走出这间教室
walking in the yard,
走在校园里
with the feeling that all your feelings
体会你的所有感受
are real fine part of human nature.
都是人性的一部分
They just are.
它们在那里
Neither good nor bad.
不论好坏
As you walk amid the buildings and trees,
在你走在建筑物和树木之间时
as you see your friends and classmates,
在你看到朋友和同学时
allow these emotions to float through you,
让那些情绪流遍你的全身
freely, lightly.
自由地 轻盈地
By experiencing these emotions,
通过体会这些情绪
whether the ups and the downs,
不论是起是落
what you are doing is being,
你正在做的是
being a human being.
作一个人
Continue to allow the breath and the emotions to just flow.
继续让呼吸和情绪流动
To just be.
任其流动
What if you truly gave yourself the permission to be human?
如果你真的能准许自己为人呢?
What if you are giving yourself the permission to be human?
如果你真的准许自己为人呢?
Just imagine.
放飞想象
Life becomes so much lighter.
生命变得更加轻盈
So much simpler.
更加简单
When, rather than trying to fight or defeat our nature,
不是想办法战斗打败我们的本性
we accept it.
我们接受它
We accept who we are.
我们接受自己
We accept whatever emotion comes up.
我们接受出现的一切情绪
Deep, slow inhalation.
深深 缓慢地吸气
Slow, gentle, quiet, calm exhalation.
缓慢 平稳 安静 平静地呼气
Take a few deep breaths in silence.
安静地深呼吸几次
Embrace the silence, the stillness.
拥抱这份安静 静止
Embrace yourself, your emotions.
拥护你自己 你的情绪
And on your next exhalation--
下次呼气
deep, slow, quiet exhalation,
深深 缓慢 安静地呼气
open your eyes.
睁开你的眼睛
If the person next to you is asleep,
如果你身边的人睡着了
gently wake him or her up.
轻轻地把他或她唤醒
Just imagine
放飞想象
Just imagine the kind of life that you can experience --
想象你将体验怎样的生活
hush-- the kind of life you can lead,
你将拥有怎样的生活
if you truly, genuinely,
如果你真的
really gave yourself the permission to be human.
准许自己为人
It's one of the pillars of healthy life,
它是健康人生的支柱之一
psychologically, physiologically.
不论是心理上还是身体上
So try it.
试试吧
Everyday remind yourself just once or twice
每天提醒自己一两次
to give yourself the permission to be human.
准许自己为人
And give others that same permission.
同样也准许别人这样做
You deserve it.
你们应得的
周四见